Guide to the Zdenek Nemeck Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
The alphabetically arranged letters of Series I, Correspondence, are divided into incoming and outgoing sections. The correspondence is almost all in Czech. The letters were received from and dispatched to a variety of countries such as Denmark, Germany, Canada, Great Britain, Sweden, France, Italy, Czechoslovakia, and Yugoslavia. They have similar contents, mostly related to Nemecek's literary activities and his interactions with publishers, translators, and collaborators. Some correspondents ask for help or literary contributions, while others write friendly letters, praising his work and congratulating him on his success. Some of the best known correspondents are Marie Polenská, Peter Demetz, Hanna Demetz, Ladislav Matejka, Bohumil Janda, Else Westh Neuhard, and Milada Soucková. The collection also contains a carbon of a June 6, 1953 letter from Nemecek to Czeslaw Milosz. Of special interest is an invitation which Nemecek received from the Ministry of Education to take part in the salutation of President Edvard Benes on the occasion of his return to Prague from London, after his voluntary exile during the German occupation (Box 1, folder 24). Another notable letter is from Ladislav Síma, thanking Nemecek for the financial support which his wife received (from Edvard Benes' special fund in London) during his imprisonment under the Germans (Box 1, folder 39).
Only occasionally does Nemecek write about his worries, difficulties, and health problems. Some letters relate to his radio work. There are only a handful of family letters as, for example, Nemecek's letter to his wife Anna from Pankrác prison in Prague (Box 2, folder 61).
Additional letters, strictly business, can be found in Writings under the individual titles of novels, dramas, or short stories. Personal letters received on occasion of Nemecek's sixtieth birthday, and the letters of sympathy addressed to his widow Anna Nemecková and, eventually, to their daughter Olga Brzorádová, are located in Series IV, as are a few of his "last" letters (Box 26, folder 855). Series V, Other Papers, also contains some letters in the PEN club folder. The Third Party letters are housed in one folder.
Series II, Writings, is divided into seven alphabetically arranged subseries. The first houses Novels and has papers on six titles. A typescript is found for Na pocátku bylo slovo and four tentative drafts, arranged in order of creation, for Tvrdá zeme. The rest of the titles have only related material, such as author's fees and royalties, contracts, correspondence with publishers and translators, reviews, or rejection notes. Preservation copies of reviews have been made where needed.
The second subseries, Drama, Boxes 6-7, is divided into one-act and multiple-act plays. Of the seventeen one-act plays, twelve have texts (typescripts, holographs, or mimeographs), and the rest have only related material, such as publishing, presentation, and business records. Two are in English, and one in Danish. Nine plays with more than one act are represented in the collection. Four have texts (drafts, typescripts, mimeographs), the rest have only related materials, with additional playbills.
Nemecek wrote three Travel Books, which form the third subseries and are housed in one box. They are Dopisy ze Senegambie, Islandské dopisy, and Západoindicky deník. Texts are not included. Besides describing the history, cultures, and peoples of those foreign places, Nemecek also presents local problems as he observed them, without suggesting solutions. Ferdinand Peroutka, writing about Nemecek's successful travel books, comments that he did not write them because he traveled, but that he traveled in order to be able to write them.
The collection holds numerous Short Stories, which comprise the fourth subseries. Most are in typescript form. Some individual stories, such as Balada o dokonalosti, Filatelista, Manhattan, Pojistka, Stin and Svetlo vecné were gathered together and published as a collection under the title Stín a jiné povídky. The story Konec beze slov forms the sixth and final chapter of the book Na pocátku bylo slovo. Also included is a collection of stories Legionárské novely. Some stories are accompanied by related records. There are ten stories in English translation, two in French, and one each in German, Afrikaans, and Dutch.
The fifth subseries, Poetry, is composed of sixty-four typescripts, holographs, or poems published in newspapers. Some were published in Czech newspapers, such as Novy domov, New yorské noviny, Sklizen, Lidové noviny, and Svoboda. Some poems were written for special occasions, while others show Nemecek's sudden need to express his feelings and emotions. Fragile newspaper clippings have been preserved by photocopying.
The articles, interviews, reviews, and speeches of subseries six, Shorter Works, are housed in one box. They include twenty-seven articles and six interviews and reviews. The titles clearly indicate the subjects. These works are represented mostly by typescripts, but sometimes there are newspaper clippings. Nemecek's last interview took place in Copenhagen on July 2, 1957 for the Danish newspaper Politiken. His speeches document his involvement in the political life of Czech immigrants and his continuous, uninterrupted emotional attachment to his native land. They are arranged alphabetically by title. They were given on such occasions as the anniversary of the proclamation of Czechoslovakian independence on October 28, 1918, the reinstatement of the republic after the German occupation, the Communist coup d'état in February 1948, the anniversary of President Masaryk's birth in 1950, and other such occasions.
Subseries seven, Radio Scripts, forms one of the largest and most important parts of Writings. The radio scripts help divide Nemecek's life into two chapters. The first period ends with the Communist coup d'état in February 1948. Before that he had his country to serve. During that time, he produced almost all of his literary work. In his books, he often wrote about Czech immigrants and their struggles, but could not understand or accept why they would leave their country for materialistic reasons, choosing voluntarily to become émigrés. After the Communist takeover, he became an involuntary political emigrant, an uprooted and homeless individual. He wrote fewer full length works, and dedicated himself more fully to radio, which gave him the opportunity to be close to his country by sending home information and messages that people eagerly awaited. This part of the collection forms the nucleus of the papers.
The radio scripts are divided into four sections, arranged chronologically and then alphabetically: Czechoslovak Radio (Ceskoslovensky rozhlas), Canadian Broadcasting Corporation (CBC), Voice of America (VOA), and Radio Free Europe (RFE: Svobodná Evropa. Hlas Svobodného Ceskoslovenska). Radio Free Europe scripts are further subdivided into those written by Nemecek, Radio Scripts of Others, and Unidentified. Within these divisions, the scripts are arranged alphabetically by subject and then alphabetically by title. On occasion, Nemecek provided some material for Czechoslovak Radio. He also worked as a freelancer for CBC, as well as for VOA. Radio Free Europe broadcasting in New York became his permanent place of work.
The main groups (and the largest), of the RFE are: "Kulturní zpravodajství" (Cultural News), "Slovo a svet" (In the Mood), which at the beginning of June 1957, was changed to "Culture and Man," and "Vzkazy domovu [a z domova]" (Messages Home and From Home). Then follow twenty-five miscellaneous smaller groups, also alphabetically arranged according to the name of the program and then the titles. These groups are "Abeceda democracie" (ABC of Democracy); "Bumerang"; "Cteme ze zákazanych knih" (Reading Aloud); "Delnické zpravodajství z Ameriky" (Labor Program from America); "Denní komentár k mezinárodní situaci" (International Commentary); "Denní zprávy z Ameriky" (Daily Report From America); "Dopis z Nového Yorku" (Letter From New York); "Drobnicka" (Short News From America); "Hra tydne" (Play of the Week); "Jak tomu opravdu bylo" (How It Really Happened); "Kniha tydne" (Book of the Week); "Kulturní program" (Cultural Program); "Národohospodársky porad" (Economic Program); "Nase první republika" (Our First Republic); "Nejlepsí clánek dne" (The Best Article of the Day); "Americe z Ameriky" (Inside USA); "O zivote v sovetském svete" (From Official Soviet Sources); "[Politické] komentáre" (Local -, Night- Special Commentaries; Spotlight); "Profil tydne" (Who is Who); "Voláme komunistickou stranu" (Calling C. P.); "Vyucujeme dejepisu" (Teaching History); "Za zeleznou oponou" (Iron Curtain News); "Zemedelství na západe" (Agriculture in the West); "Zivot a cestování ve svobodném svete" (Life and Travel). All these manuscripts are in typescript or mimeograph form. Most titles indicate clearly the subjects of the groups. The largest group, "Slovo a svet" (In the Mood) contains around 115 titles. Some scripts are excerpted works of others, translated and adopted for radio by Nemecek. At the beginning of such radio programs, an explanation of the title "Slovo a svet" is given: "The poets, artists and thinkers of all times and of all nations speak to you. In the times of a confusion of all values, the creative word has the power of giving strengths to a human being and of leading him to fight for truth and justice." Later, another simple explanation was given, meaning: "V dobré nálade."
One of the politically charged programs is "Vzkazy domovu [a z domova]" (Messages). The explanation is as follows: "Letters from one operating group in Bohemia... written in Czechoslovakia and mailed abroad, not far from the Czechoslovak frontier, were received here (in the United States) and then answers were broadcast back [to Czechoslovakia]." Nemecek was the inspiration for this program. All the details about these messages, the copies of the letters and the codes used, can be found in the collection. It was a very effective program. It also includes a letter from the Czechoslovak group to President Eisenhower, written on May 30, 1953, and the answer of C. D. Jackson to Dr. Julius Firt, then head of the Czechoslovak Service (Box 19, folder 667).
Many subjects are covered in the radio programs. Some concern the political situation in Czechoslovakia, Poland, Hungary, Soviet Union; others are on books and publishers, the American market and theaters; and still others are devoted to writers such as Albert Camus, Joseph Conrad, Josef and Karel Capek, Vladimir Dudintsev, William Faulkner, Ernest Hemingway, Victor Hugo, Karel Hynek Mácha, Maurice Rowdon, and Josef Kajetán Tyl. Other subjects include music and musicians, films and television, Czechs in America (Rudolf Firkusny, Jirí Voskovec, and Rafael Kubelík for example), singers, philosophy and philosophers, Czech Legionaries, and such well-known figures as Dr. Edvard Benes, Sigmund Freud, Winston Churchill, and Jan Masaryk. The Canadian programs discuss many Canadian topics.
The Radio Scripts of Others contain nine articles, mostly mimeographs. Two are about Nemecek, accompanied by excerpts from Tvrdá zeme and New York: zamlzeno. Folder 764 contains a series of F. Peroutka's "Talks."
Series III, Writings of Others is housed in three boxes. The first box contains Works on Nemecek by Beatrice M. Nosco in English and Czech, both typescripts. It is followed by Miscellaneous writings which includes a complete set (except two issues) of Novoe russkoe slovo, where V. D. Dudintsev's work Ne khlebom edinym appeared on continuation. There is also a fragment of Nemecek's translation into Czech. Among other works are Nemecek's translations into Czech of four poems by S. Kessler, A. Bontemps, and L. Alexander.
Series IV, Personal Papers is divided into nine subseries. Nemecek's "last" correspondence (Box 26, folder 855), contrasts with the letters of congratulation on his sixtieth birthday ( Box 27, folder 901), which are joyful, full of respect, admiration and appreciation, describing him above all as an exceptional human being.
The third section called Death and Memorial Tributes, has five further subdivisions. Seven folders of letters of sympathy attest to how highly he was esteemed, respected, and loved (folders 857-63). There are eighteen obituaries (folders 866-83) written by friends and published in such newspapers as New yorské listy, Denní hlasatel, Sklizen and Americké noviny. In order to preserve information, these fragile papers have been photocopied. Two obituaries were never published.
Besides written memorial tributes, Nemecek was also honored by such organizations as the Czechoslovak Society of Arts and Sciences, the National Council of Women of Free Czechoslovakia, and the PEN club. Nemecek was honored by seven Radio Free Europe broadcasts dedicated to him. A surprising broadcasting commemorating Nemecek came on February 2, 1969, from Czechoslovak Radio in Prague, written by Miroslav Ivanov. It marked the first time since 1948, when all of Nemecek's books were banned in his own country that his name and the message about him was carried clearly and loudly on the radio waves.
Only a few photographs are in the collection. The most valuable are those made in Copenhagen on July 3 and 4, 1957, shortly before his death, when he was visiting his old friend Else Westh Neuhard. Photographs of his wife and daughter Olga and a few friends are also included in the collection.
The last series, in one box called Other Papers, houses a variety of material, such as two holograph signatures (1934): that of the first president of the Czechoslovakia--Tomás Garrigue Masaryk, and the second president--Dr. Edvard Benes, at that time minister of foreign affairs. Also included is correspondence of the PEN Center for Writers in Exile, American Branch, together with a handful of their publications, minutes, and other documents. Nemecek was elected chairman of the PEN club for 1956-57.
There are two boxes of oversize. The first contains 20 pages of galley proofs of illustrations created by Cyril Bouda for Nemecek's novel Evropská kantiléna and "Le Secret des Nations Unies," an article published in Le Patriote in 1960. The other box contains a valuable portfolio of a holographic certificate for Zdenek Nemecek making him an honorary citizen of the city of Rataje nad Sázavou, and a folder with a sheet from an unknown magazine illustrating the "Hrazené Rataje."
The Zdenek Nemecek Papers are the first Czech collection to be acquired by the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. The focal person is a figure extraordinaire and, as he said himself, he "has seen it all": both Russian revolutions, combat in World War I, the first "steps" of Hitler in Nürnberg, the Spanish Civil War, the German occupation of his country including "the delights" of a political prisoner, the resurrection of Czechoslovakia (1945), kings and beggars, the Communist takeover of his country (1948) and, finally, exile. One can study not only Nemecek's rich life, but also his works, his thoughts, his surroundings, and all that which enriches our knowledge of the political and literary history of Czech emigration. His radio scripts present a wide range of research possibilities. Knowledge of Czech is required to discover the treasures, but it is hoped that those with the necessary abilities will study the papers and disseminate the results of their research.
Authors, Czech -- 20th Century; Communism -- Czechoslovakia; Communism -- Soviet Union; Czechs -- United States; Poets, Czech -- 20th Century; Political refugees; Radio in propaganda; Bohemia and Moravia (Protectorate, 1939-1945); Czechoslovakia -- Economic conditions -- 1945-1992; Czechoslovakia -- History -- 1938-1945; Czechoslovakia -- History -- Coup d'état, 1948; Czechoslovakia -- Politics and government; Radio scripts -- Czechoslovakia; Radio broadcasters -- United States; Beneš, Edvard, 1884-1948; Čapek, Josef, 1887-1945; Čapek, Karel, 1890-1938; Chekhov, Anton Pavlovich, 1860-1904; Dudint͡sev, Vladimir, 1918-1998; Firt, Julius, 1897-; Hájek, Josef; Hostovský, Egon, 1908-1973; Ivanov, Miroslav; Jílovský, Rudolf, 1890-1954; Masaryk, Jan, 1886-1948; Masaryk, T. G. (Tomáš Garrigue), 1850-1937; Matejka, Ladislav, 1919-2012; Němeček, Anna; Němeček, Zdeněk, 1894-1957; Neuhard, Else Westh; Nosco, Beatrice M.; Peroutka, Ferdinand, 1895-1978; Součková, Milada, 1899-1983; Canadian Broadcasting Corporation; Československý rozhlas; Radio Free Europe; Voice of America (Organization)
- Correspondence, 1925-79; Series I; 0.75; (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is divided into three alphabetically arranged subseries: Incoming, Outgoing, and Third Party.
  - INCOMING
    - Zdenek Nemecek
      - "A" general, 1946-56 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Arkenberg, Dr. B., 1950-56 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
      - "B" general, 1934-56 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Boucek, J. A., 1950-54 (Box 1, Folder 2a)
      - "C" general, 1940-57, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
      - "Cin", 1940-44 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - "D" general, 1933-55, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
      - "E" general, 1940-55 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - European Overseas Exchange Company, 1953-54, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8a)
      - "F" general, 1935-56 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Firt, Julius, 1948-50 (Box 1, Folder 9a)
      - Fr. Borovy, nakladatelství. Praha, 1941-47 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - "G" general, 1940-46, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Glydendalske, Boghandel Nordisk, Forlag, 1948-50 (Box 1, Folder 11a)
      - Granville, M. P.
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: Polenská, Marie, Box 2, folder 36
      - "H" general, 1940-56, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
      - "I" general, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 13a)
      - International PEN Club, 1953-56 (Box 1, Folder 13b)
        See also: Series IV, Box 27, folders 895-96
      - "J" general, 1938-57, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Jakerlová (Jakerle), Maren, 1946-56 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Jakerle, Jirí, 1946 Oct 9 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Jandera, Jaroslav, 1951-56 (Box 1, Folder 15a)
      - Jaromer, Czechoslovakia, 1940-45 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Javor, Pavet, 1953-56 (Box 1, Folder 16a)
      - Jirák, Karel B., 1951-54 (Box 1, Folder 16b)
      - John, Jaromír, 1940-43 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Josefov n./Met., Czechoslovakia, 1932-47 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - "K" general, 1938-60, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
      - Klika, Karel, 1955-56 (Box 1, Folder 20a)
      - Kolár, Jan M. and Aja, 1951-59, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20b)
      - Kutík, Karel, 1945-50 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - "L" general, 1936-57 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - "M" general, 1940-57 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
      - Matejka, Ladislav, 1955-57, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
      - "N" general, 1936-56 (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
      - Nakladatelství Fr. Vacera, Josefov n./Met., 1940-46 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Nakladatelství Karel Synek, Praha, 1946-47 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Nakladatelství Sfinx. Bohumil Janda, Praha, 1935-48 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Necas, Frantisek, 1956-57 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Neuhard, Else Westh, 1949-57, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32a)
      - "O" general, 1940-57 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - "P" general, 1941-57 (Box 2, Folder 34-35)
      - Pitskerová, G. M.
      - Polenská, Marie, 1953-56 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - "R" general, 1940-57 (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Rady Svobodného Ceskoslovenska, 1949-55 (Box 2, Folder 37a)
      - Rataje nad Sázavou, Czechoslovakia, 1940-46 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - Reptis, Pavel, 1949-52 (Box 2, Folder 38a)
      - "S" general, 1940-56, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 39-41)
      - Sátora, Ing. F., 1950-56 (Box 2, Folder 41a)
      - Soucková, Milada, 1955-57 (Box 2, Folder 42-43)
      - Syndikát ceskych spisovatelu. Praha, 1942-48 (Box 2, Folder 44)
      - "T" general, 1940-57 (Box 2, Folder 45)
      - "U" general, 1940-54 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      - "V" general, 1940-57, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 47)
      - Vlach, Ant., 1954-55 (Box 2, Folder 47a)
      - Vlach, Robert, 1955-56 (Box 2, Folder 47a)
      - "W" general, 1941-54 (Box 2, Folder 48)
      - "Z" general, 1942-52 (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - Unidentified, 1935-56, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Anna Nemecková
      - Brzorád, Vilém, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 51)
      - "D-S" general and envelopes, 1945-79 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - OUTGOING
    - Zdenek Nemecek
      - "A-B" general, 1947-56 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      - "C" general, 1946-56 (Box 2, Folder 53a)
      - "D-E" general, 1945-57, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 54)
      - "F-G" general, 1946-56 (Box 2, Folder 54a)
      - "H" general, 1950-57 (Box 2, Folder 55)
      - International PEN Club, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 55a)
      - "J" general, 1946-56 (Box 2, Folder 55b)
      - "K" general, 1946-57 (Box 2, Folder 56)
      - Kolár, Jan M. and Aja, 1952-57 (Box 2, Folder 56a)
      - "L-M" general (includes letter to Milosz), 1941-57 (Box 2, Folder 57)
      - Matejka, Vladislav, 1955-57 (Box 2, Folder 58)
      - "N" general, 1943-57, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 59)
      - Nakladatelství Sfinx. Bohumil Janda, Praha, 1946-47 (Box 2, Folder 60)
      - Nemecková, Anna, [1945] (Box 2, Folder 61)
      - Neuhard, Else Westh, 1954-57 (Box 2, Folder 61a)
      - "O-P" general, 1952-57 (Box 2, Folder 62)
      - "R" general, 1941-56, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 62a)
      - "S-V" general, 1947-57 (Box 2, Folder 63)
      - Sátora, Ing. F., 1952-56 (Box 2, Folder 63a)
      - Soucková, Milada, 1955-57 (Box 2, Folder 64)
      - "T-Z" general, 1950-57 (Box 2, Folder 64a)
      - Vlach, Robert, 1955-57 (Box 2, Folder 64b)
      - Unidentified, 1952-57 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - OUTGOING
    - Anna Nemecková
      - "H" general, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - THIRD PARTY
    - "C-U" general, 1925-57 (Box 2, Folder 67)
- Writings, 1925-71; Series II; 6.25; (20 boxes)
  Series II, Writings is divided into seven subseries: Novels (Boxes 3-5), Drama (Boxes 6-7), Travel Books (Box 8), Short Stories (Boxes 9-10), Poetry (Box 11), Shorter Works (Box 12) and Radio Scripts (Boxes 13-22). Shorter Works is further subdivided into three sections: Articles, Interviews and Reviews, and Speeches. The subseries Radio Scripts is subdivided into four sections: Czechoslovak Radio, Canadian Broadcasting Corporation (CBC), Voice of America, (VOA), and Radio Free Europe (RFE). Radio Free Europe is further subdivided into Scripts of Nemecek, Scripts of Others, and Unidentified. The material is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - NOVELS
    - "D'ábel mluví spanelsky"
      See also: Box 1, folder 31, Box 2, folder 60
      - Contracts and royalties, 1939-48 (Box 3, Folder 68)
      - Correspondence about translations, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 69)
      - Reviews, 1939-40 (Box 3, Folder 70)
      - Second Czech Prize, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - "Evropská kantiléna"
      See: Oversize: Box 29, folder 920
      See also: Box 1, folder 31; Box 2, folder 60
      - Author's fees, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 72)
      - Contracts, 1945, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 73)
      - Correspondence about translations, 1946-47 (Box 3, Folder 74)
      - Correspondence with publishers, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 75)
      - Publicity, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 76)
      - Reviews, 1947-49, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - "Kanadská rapsodie"
      See: "Tvrdá zeme", Box 4, folder 96
    - "Na pocátku bylo slovo"
      See also: Box 2, folder 56 (Koldo)
      - Chapters I - VI: typescripts, [1954?] (Box 3, Folder 78-84)
    - "Na západ od Panonie"
      - Awards and congratulations, 1935, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 85)
      - Contracts, 1935, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 86)
      - Correspondence about the translations, 1935-37 (Box 3, Folder 87)
      - Correspondence with publishers, 1935-36 (Box 3, Folder 88)
      - Publicity, [1935?] (Box 3, Folder 89)
      - Reviews, 1935, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 90)